Rush family papers LCP.Rush
Library Company of Philadelphia
The John Rush papers include letters from John Rush to his father, Dr. Benjamin Rush, as well other documents, particularly on land purchases. John Rush earned his degree in medicine from the University of Pennsylvania (diploma included) in 1804 and served in the United States Navy in 1802 and again from 1805 to 1808, when he commanded gunboats in Boston and New Orleans. According to Binger, “on October 1, 1807, he fought a duel with Lieutenant Benjamin Taylor, in command of Gunboat No. 15 at the New Orleans Station [and] Taylor was killed,” (Binger, page 282). Apparently, Taylor had been a good friend of Rush’s and after a brief arrest, he was able to return to duty, however, he continued to run into trouble and eventually, in 1810, he tried to commit suicide, was described as “insane,” and was “brought home in February 1810 in a state of deep melancholy,” (Binger, page 282). He was treated by his father in the Pennsylvania Hospital until Dr. Benjamin Rush’s death in 1813, and remained in the Pennsylvania Hospital until his own death in 1837.
The Richard Rush papers include letters from much of Richard’s professional life from 1801 to 1849. One volume of letters documents Richard’s auspicious career as Attorney General of Pennsylvania during the year 1811. His papers also contain a manuscript for the book, Residence at the Court of London, which was published in 1872 and describes Richard’s experiences as Minister from the United States from 1817 to 1825.
The William Rush papers consists of four folders of letters from William to his mother Julia Rush from 1823 to 1832 and one volume, Examinations on Materia Medica in the Philadelphia School of Medicine, given by him as lecturer on materia medica and therapeutics at the Philadelphia School of Medicine, in 1832.
Correspondence, diaries, genealogies and diplomas consist of material created by various Rush family members. These materials are arranged chronologically. Included are Cassie Murray Rush’s diary from 1876 in which she describes a visit to the Centennial; Phoebe Anne Rush's music book presented to her in 1820 by Frank Johnson, a black Philadelphia musician; The “Miscellaneous documents” series contains materials that cannot be attributed to any one member of the Rush family. Materials include letters, poems, tickets, manuscripts, and the size of G. Colburn’s head. These materials are largely undated and are not addressed to anyone.
Bibliography:
Binger, Carl, M.D. Revolutionary Doctor, Benjamin Rush, 1746-1813. W. W. Norton & Company, Inc.: New York, 1966.
Goodman, Nathan G. Benjamin Rush: Physician and Citizen, 1746-1813. University of Pennsylvania Press: Philadelphia, 1934.
Historical Society of Berks County. Transactions of the Historical Society of Berks County, Volume I. B.F. Owen & Co.: Reading, PA, 1904.
Pennsylvania. Department of General Services. http://www.dgs.state.pa.us/portal/server.pt/gateway/PTARGS_6_2_36586_4287_472644_43/
Related Archival Materials note
College of Physicians of Philadelphia: Benjamin Rush papers, undated.
Duke University Medical Center Library: Benjamin Rush papers, 1766-1845.
Library of Congress: Benjamin Rush papers, 1776-1812.
Presbyterian Historical Society: Benjamin Rush papers, 1767 and 1783
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Bequest of James Rush, 1869.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research use, on deposit at the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, 1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA 19107. For access, please contact the Historical Society at 215-732-6200 or visit http://www.hsp.org.
Biographical/Historical note
The Rush Family papers includes material from Benjamin Rush, physician, social activist, educator, writer and patriot; his brother Jacob Rush, lawyer, Supreme Court judge, and patriot; and Benjamin’s son James Rush, physician and Treasurer of the United States Mint. These American men were “strong characters, zealous patriots during the stirring period in which they lived, tenacious of their convictions and of the high standard of individual duty which they set for others, and typified in themselves,” (Richards, page 53).
Benjamin Rush
Benjamin Rush, a physician, social activist, educator, writer, and patriot, was born on December 24, 1745 at Byberry, Pennsylvania, the fourth child of John and Susanna (Hall) Rush. He was educated at the College of New Jersey, now called Princeton University, graduating at age 15; and the University of Edinburgh in Scotland where he earned his degree of Medical Doctor in June 1768. Prior to traveling to Scotland, Rush studied under Dr. John Redmond of Philadelphia and took classes at the College of Philadelphia, now called the University of Pennsylvania, taught by Dr. William Shippen, Jr. and Dr. John Morgan in 1754. He began practicing medicine when he returned to Philadelphia.
In 1775, Rush met and fell in love with Julia Stockton of Princeton, New Jersey and they were married in January 1776. They had thirteen children, four of whom died in infancy. Benjamin and Julia Rush’s children were: John, Anne Emily (1779-1850), Richard (1780-1859), Susannah (died in infancy), Elizabeth (died in infancy), Mary, James (1786-1869), William (died in infancy), Benjamin (died in infancy), Benjamin (1791-1824), Julia (1792-1860), Samuel (1795-1859), and William.
As a physician, the role for which Rush is best known, he was dedicated and untiring. He founded the Philadelphia Dispensary for the Relief of the Poor and through his “thirty years of service as a senior physician at the Pennsylvania Hospital,” the staff of which he joined in 1783, he instituted many “reforms … in the care of the mentally ill” (Princeton University). He is the author of Medical Inquiries and Observations upon the Diseases of the Mind. He wrote “prolifically on the subject of medicine and medical practice, developing a reputation as a man of literature as well as medicine,” (Dickinson College). His treatments of purging and bloodletting during the yellow fever epidemic of 1793 created great controversy. “In the devastating yellow fever epidemics which afflicted Philadelphia in the 1790s, Rush labored among the sick and dying, morning and night, was felled by the disease himself, and never doubted that his prescriptions of heroic purging and bleeding had saved hundreds of lives,” (Rush, page xvi). However, “it was said of him that his purges were meant for a horse, not a man, and that he had waded through the epidemic in a bath of his patients’ blood. He was even charged with murdering them by his excessive bloodletting,” (Binger, page 227). Soon after the epidemics, Rush sued William Cobbett, also known as “Peter Porcupine” for slander. Although Rush won this suit, many were not convinced and Cobbett continued his attacks on Rush, claiming “to have established mathematically that Rush had killed more patients than he cured,” (Binger, page 247). In the years following the epidemic, Rush’s prominence in the community outweighed the controversy and “in his later years, Benjamin Rush’s reputation and fame spread beyond the parochial confines of his native state and even across the Atlantic.” (Binger, page 284).
Benjamin Rush was also “a social activist, a prominent advocate for the abolition of slavery, an advocate for scientific education for the masses, including women, and for public clinics to treat the poor,” (U.S. History). Furthermore, he favored “universal education and health care; he advocated prison reform, the abolition of … capital punishment, temperance, and better treatment of mental illness” (Dickinson College). He served as a member of American Philosophical Society and as a member of the Sons of Liberty in Philadelphia. He helped organize the Pennsylvania Society for Promoting the Abolition of Slavery and the Relief of Free Negroes Unlawfully Held in Bondage, serving, for a period of time, as president. He also became a member of the Philadelphia Society for Alleviating the Miseries of Public Prisons. As a Renaissance man, politics did not escape Rush’s notice. In 1776, Rush was elected to and represented Pennsylvania at the Continental Congress and he signed the Declaration of Independence. In 1777, he was appointed surgeon-general of the Continental Army, but quickly resigned because he “became outraged by the conditions he found in army hospitals and, failing to get the remedial action he sought from the director general, Dr. Shippen (his former teacher), he sent a protest to General Washington, accusing Dr. Shippen of maladministration,” (Princeton University). When Congress ruled in favor of Shippen, Rush’s military career ended. Rush supported a federal constitution and in 1787, he voiced his opinions “to advocate the ratification of the federal constitution; his actions let to an appointment to the ratifying convention for the state,” (Dickinson College). He was appointed treasurer of the United States Mint and served from 1797 until his death in 1813.
Education was also important to Rush. Appointed chair of Chemistry at the College of Philadelphia in 1769, Rush became “at the age of twenty-three the first professor of chemistry in America,” (Princeton University). He also served as professor of medical theory and clinical practice at the College of Pennsylvania, and “all told, he taught more than three thousand medical students, who carried his influence to every corner of the growing nation,” (Princeton University). In 1783, he founded Dickinson College, and “serv[ed] as one of the most influential trustees of the College from its founding until his death.” (Dickinson College). According to Carl Binger, “on September 9, 1783, six days after the peace treaty with England went into effect, the Legislature passed an act to establish the College at Carlisle in Cumberland County,” (Binger, page 166) making Dickinson College the first institution of higher education in the United States. He also served as a charter trustee of Franklin College, now Franklin and Marshall College, and as an incorporator of the Young Ladies Academy in Philadelphia.
Benjamin Rush died on April 19, 1813 at age 67. Despite disagreeing with some of Rush’s tactics, Thomas Jefferson, at the time of Rush’s death, wrote in a letter to John Adams, “a better man than Rush could not have left us, more benevolent, more learned, of finer genius or more honest,” (Binger, page 296). John Adams similarly honored Rush saying, “as a man of Science, Letters, Task, Sense, Phylosophy, Patriotism, Religion, Morality, Merit, Usefulness, taken all together, Rush has not left his equal in America, nor that I know of in the world,” (Binger, page 296).
Jacob Rush
Jacob Rush, brother of Benjamin Rush and son of John and Susan Harvey Rush, was born November 24, 1747 in Byberry Township, Philadelphia County. He obtained his education from Francis Allison at a school in New London, Chester County, the Academy at Nottingham, Cecil County, MD, and the College of New Jersey (now Princeton University), earning the degree of Doctor of Laws. He was admitted to the Philadelphia Bar on February 7, 1769 and to the Bar in Berks County on May 10, 1769.
Rush was elected as a member of the Assembly from Philadelphia County in 1782 and served until his resignation on March 20, 1784 when he was appointed “by the Supreme Executive Council to the Supreme Bench, in the room of John Evans, deceased,” (Richards, page 56). After the judiciary system was changed by State constitution in 1790, Rush was commissioned President of the Third Circuit on August 17, 1791. According to Richards, Rush was a strong Federalist, believe in “the maintenance of social order by the literal and rigid enforcement of the Act of 1794, against vice and immorality—contemptuously referred to as the Blue Law—passed during his administration,” (Richards, page 66).
The judicial circuits were reorganized in 1806, and Rush was commissioned president of the district of the City and County of Philadelphia. Rush served on the Bench of the District Court of Philadelphia from 1811 until his death.
Rush had married Mary Rench in 1777. They had four daughters who survived both Rush and his wife who died on August 31, 1806. Rush died on January 5, 1820 at the age of 73. It was said that “his uprightness of conduct and unquestionable abilities always secured him the respect and confidence, if not the attachment of his associates, the members of the Bar and the entire community,” (Richards, page 60).
James Rush
James Rush, born March 1, 1786, was the seventh son of Dr. Benjamin Rush. He studied medicine at Princeton University and the University of Edinburgh. He also earned his medical degree at the University of Pennsylvania in 1809. He did not practice medicine regularly and in 1813 was appointed Treasurer of the United States Mint where he served until 1830.
James Rush married Phoebe Anne Ridgeway (1799-1857) a Philadelphia heiress and he inherited her fortune after her death in 1857. In his will, Rush left the bulk of his estate to the Library Company of Philadelphia for the building of the Ridgeway Branch. He was the author of The Philosophy of the Human Voice and “achieved a high reputation as a physician, but later in life secluded himself among his books,” (Scharf, page 1186).
Bibliography:
Binger, Carl, M.D. Revolutionary Doctor: Benjamin Rush, 1746-1813. New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc., 1996.
Dickinson College. Benjamin Rush (1745-1813). http://chronicles.dickinson.edu/encyclo/r/ed_rushB.html (accessed March 2, 2010).
Princeton University. Campus Companion. http://etcweb.princeton.edu/CampusWWW/Companion/rush_benjamin.html (accessed March 2, 2010).
Richards, Louis. “Honorable Jacob Rush of the Pennsylvania Judiciary,” The Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography. Vol. 39, No. 1 (1915).
Rush, Benjamin. My Dearest Julia: the love letters of Dr. Benjamin Rush to Julia Stockton. New York: Neale Watson Academic Publications, Inc., 1979.
Sharf, J. Thomas and Thompson Westcott. History of Philadelphia, 1609-1884, Volume 2. Philadelphia: L.H. Everts & Co., 1884.
U.S. History. Biographical Sketch of Benjamin Rush. http://www.ushistory.org/declaration/signers/rush.htm (accessed March 2, 2010).
Other Finding Aids note
Researchers should note that a physical card catalog pre-dates the processing and finding aid created during the 2009-2011 PACSCL/CLIR "Hidden Collections" processing project. A partial alphabetical list of correspondents filed under "Rush" in this card catalog was transcribed and can be found here: http://www.lcpimages.org/lcpAT/pdf/RushBenjamin_alpha%20correspondence.pdf
Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815; Boudinot, Elias, 1740-1821; College of New Jersey (Princeton, N.J.).; Dickinson College.; Dickinson, John, 1732-1808; Eustis, William, 1753-1825; Fergusson, Elizabeth Graeme, 1737-1801; Hosack, David, 1769-1835; Lettsom, John Coakley, 1744-1815; Nisbet, Charles, 1736-1804; Percival, Thomas, 1740-1804; Ramsay, David, 1749-1815; Rush, Benjamin, 1746-1813; Rush, Jacob, 1747-1820; Rush, James, 1786-1869; Rush, John, 1777-1837; Rush, Julia Stockton; Rush, Richard, 1780-1859; Rush, William, 1801-1864; Shippen, William, 1736?-1808; United States. Constitutional Convention (1787).; United States. Continental Congress.; United States. Navy.; University of Edinburgh.; University of Pennsylvania. Dept. of Medicine.; Abolitionists; Authors, American; Commonplace books; Correspondence; Diaries; Estate records; Family papers; Financial records; Lecture notes; Lectures; Manuscripts; Medical education; Medicine; Mental illness; Pennsylvania--History; Pennsylvania--History--1775-1865; Pennsylvania--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Philadelphia (Pa.); Physicians; Poems; Property records; Textbooks; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783; Yellow fever
- Series I. Benjamin Rush papers
  - Subseries I: Correspondence
    - A. Bound volumes
      Scope and Contents note
      Volumes 1, 2, 2a, 30 and 34 have been disbound and were boxed. Individual correspondents have been listed for disbound volumes. The catalog numbers for these volumes are:
      Volume 1: Yi2 7216 Volume 2: Yi2 7217 Volume 2a: Yi2 7218 Volume 30: Yi2 7246 Volume 34: Yi2 7250
      - Aaggiz, Jef, 1780 March 28 (Volume 1, Page 1)
      - Adair, William, undated (Volume 1, Page 2)
      - Adams, Joseph, 1799, undated (Volume 1, Page 5-6)
      - Adams, T.B., 1802 May 29 (Volume 1, Page 7)
      - Adamson, John, 1810 November 1 (Volume 1, Page 9)
      - Adamson, William, 1804 June 7 (Volume 1, Page 8)
      - Addison, Alex, [1786] August 10-1793 January 21 (Volume 1, Page 3-4)
      - A Friend to Genious [sic], 1803 December 1 (Volume 1, Page 129)
      - A Friend to Improvement, 1812 November 13 (Volume 1, Page 133)
      - Agnew, Samuel, 1803-1811 (Volume 1, Page 10-19)
      - Albertina, Dr. Charles, 1812 June 25 (Volume 1, Page 75)
      - Alexander T., 1811 February 21 (Volume 1, Page 41)
      - Alexander, Archibald, 1800 January 11 (Volume 1, Page 31)
      - Alexander, Ashton, 1796-1797 (Volume 1, Page 24-25)
      - Alexander, Ashton, 1798-1799 (Volume 1, Page 27-29)
      - Alexander, Ashton, 1800-1809 (Volume 1, Page 32-35)
      - Alexander, Ashton, 1810-1813 (Volume 1, Page 39-40)
      - Alexander, Ashton, 1795, undated (Volume 1, Page 42-62)
      - Alexander, Joseph, 1797 August 17 (Volume 1, Page 26)
      - Alexander, Stephen, 1810 May 5-22 (Volume 1, Page 36-37)
      - Alexander, T., 1810 July 28 (Volume 1, Page 38)
      - Alin, James, 1805 May 8 (Volume 1, Page 73)
      - Allen, Nathaniel, 1804 March 8 (Volume 1, Page 23)
      - Allen, Peter, 1808 (Volume 1, Page 22)
      - Allen, Robert, 1804-1807 (Volume 1, Page 20-21)
      - Allmin, William, 1809 October 22, 1810 (Volume 1, Page 63)
      - Allston, W., 1789-1797 (Volume 1, Page 64-66)
      - Allston, William, 1803-1806 (Volume 1, Page 67-71)
      - Alvarey, Andrew (in French), 1798 August 27 (Volume 1, Page 74)
      - Anderson, Alexander, 1791 July 16 (Volume 1, Page 84)
      - Anderson, Alexander, 1792 August 24 (Volume 1, Page 88)
      - Anderson, E. H., 1812 October 29 (Volume 1, Page 77)
      - Anderson, Edward, 1810 March 15 (Volume 1, Page 76)
      - Anderson, J.M., 1800 December 2,1803 October 31 (Volume 1, Page 79-80)
      - Anderson, J.M., 1801 November 16, undated (Volume 1, Page 86-87)
      - Anderson, J.M., 1798 May 29 (Volume 1, Page 91)
      - Anderson, J.M., 1798, 1809, undated (Volume 1, Page 93-95)
      - Anderson, J.M., 1794-1812 (Volume 1, Page 99-103)
      - Anderson, J.M. (Jr.), 1797 July 24 (Volume 1, Page 78)
      - Anderson, J.M. (Jr.), 1798 June 21 (Volume 1, Page 90)
      - Anderson, James (includes report regarding snake pills and mad dogs), 1789-1790 (Volume 1, Page 82-83)
      - Anderson, James M., 1804 September 4 (Volume 1, Page 81)
      - Anderson, James M., 1794 December 25 (Volume 1, Page 89)
      - Anderson, James M., 1795 July 14 (Volume 1, Page 92)
      - Anderson, John, 1806 June 7 (Volume 1, Page 85)
      - Andrews, Robert, 1800 July 12 (Volume 1, Page 104)
      - Ankrim, Josiah, 1812 March 22 (Volume 1, Page 72)
      - Ankrim, Josiah, 1802 July 26 (Volume 1, Page 105)
      - Archer, John, 1787-1803 (Volume 1, Page 106-112)
      - Archer, R., 1809 August 18 (Volume 1, Page 115)
      - Archer, Rebecca, 1789 March 21 (Volume 1, Page 113)
      - Archer, Robert H., 1797 (Volume 1, Page 114)
      - Archer, Robert P., 1810 December 9 (Volume 1, Page 116)
      - Ard, Joseph B., 1810 October 28 (Volume 1, Page 117)
      - Arndt, John, 1799 December 8 (Volume 1, Page 118)
      - Arndt, John, 1799 December 28 (Volume 1, Page 121)
      - Arnold, Joseph, 1808 May 28 (Volume 1, Page 119)
      - Arnott, Henry, 1799 June 15 (Volume 1, Page 120)
      - [Arttsaur] (in French), 1789 April 13 (Volume 1, Page 125)
      - Ashton, Henry, 1809 November 20 (Volume 1, Page 123)
      - Aspin, Matthew, 1788 July 22 (Volume 1, Page 122)
      - A Student of Medicine, undated (Volume 1, Page 132)
      - Atlee, Edwin A., undated (Volume 1, Page 124)
      - Austin, Andrew, 1809 March 7 (Volume 1, Page 126)
      - Autenrieth, D., undated (Volume 1, Page 127)
      - Author unknown, 1799 August 31 (Volume 1, Page 30)
      - Author unknown, undated (Volume 1, Page 130)
      - Author unknown, undated (Volume 1, Page 131)
      - Author unknown, 1803 October 19 (Volume 2, Page 4)
      - [Ayers] Eli, 1812 December 23 (Volume 1, Page 128)
      - B., J., undated (Volume 2, Page 61)
      - Bachus, A., 1807 June 29 (Volume 2, Page 2)
      - Bachus, Elizabeth, 1809 April 18 (Volume 2, Page 5)
      - Backus, Matthew, 1807 August 13 (Volume 2, Page 3)
      - Bacon, E.P., undated (Volume 2, Page 1)
      - Bailey, Samuel, 1802 September 16-November 9 (Volume 2, Page 12-13)
      - Baird, J., undated (Volume 2, Page 11)
      - Baker, Samuel, 1812 April 15 (Volume 2, Page 8)
      - Baker, William, 1770 July 2, 1807 November 9 (Volume 2, Page 6-7)
      - Baker William, 1810 January 2, 1810 November 1 (Volume 2, Page 9-10)
      - Ball, Isaac, 1800-1809 (Volume 2, Page 14-16)
      - [Baltyall], John, 1798 May 2 (Volume 2, Page 17)
      - Bamfylde, Peter, 1812 February 14 (Volume 2, Page 18-19)
      - Banes, Josiah, 1802-1812 (Volume 2, Page 20-23)
      - Barber, Luke, 1796 May 2, undated (Volume 2, Page 24-25)
      - Barbour, James, 1800 August 25 (Volume 2, Page 26)
      - Bard, Samuel, 1770 June 24 (Volume 2, Page 27)
      - Barker, Jeremy, 1806 September 22 (Volume 2, Page 28)
      - Barnard, D., 1808 October 29-30 (Volume 2, Page 34-35)
      - Barnes, Henry, 1795 April 24 (Volume 2, Page 32)
      - Barnes, John, 1812 November 16 (Volume 2, Page 29)
      - [Barnes illegible], 1770 June 1 (Volume 2, Page 30)
      - Barns, Mary, 1798 November 30 (Volume 2, Page 31)
      - Baron, Dr., 1794-1796 (Volume 2, Page 39-40)
      - Barr, William, undated (Volume 2, Page 33)
      - Barras, Rufus L., 1811 July 14 (Volume 2, Page 36)
      - Barrington, Joseph, 1794 February 10 (Volume 2, Page 38)
      - Barrington, W., 1810 June 21 (Volume 2, Page 37)
      - Barry, J., 1798 July 12 (Volume 2, Page 42)
      - Barry, Mrs., undated (Volume 2, Page 41)
      - Barstow, Seth J., 1805 April 19 (Volume 2, Page 43)
      - Bartine, David, 1802 June 9 (Volume 2, Page 44)
      - Bassett, Amos, 1793 March 18 (Volume 2, Page 45)
      - Bateman, Ephram, 1809-1810 (Volume 2, Page 46-48)
      - Batt, Sarah, 1798 August 12 (Volume 2, Page 49)
      - Battle, Jer., 1810 April 20-September 17 (Volume 2, Page 50-51)
      - Bayle, William, 1797 June 17 (Volume 2, Page 53)
      - Baylies, Gusavus, 1805 May 11 (Volume 2, Page 52)
      - Baynard, 1802 November 23 (Volume 2, Page 56)
      - Baynard, Thomas, 1802 November 30 (Volume 2, Page 57-59)
      - Baynard, Thomas and William, 1801 May 8-November 9 (Volume 2, Page 54-55)
      - Baynton, Benjamin, 1789 August 8 (Volume 2, Page 60)
      - Baynton, Rebecca, 1804 March 26 (Volume 2, Page 66)
      - Baynton, Susan, 1794-1808 (Volume 2, Page 62-65)
      - Baynton, Susan, 1809 July 5, 1812 January 8 (Volume 2, Page 67-68)
      - Beard, [John Mackie], 1813 January 21 (Volume 2, Page 90)
      - Beardslee, Daniel, 1810 April 24 (Volume 2, Page 91)
      - Beardsley, Eben., 1790 September 4 (Volume 2, Page 95)
      - Beckley, John, 1802 November 8, 1806 May 24 (Volume 2, Page 96-97)
      - Bedford, John, 1808 June 22 (Volume 2, Page 92)
      - Beech, [Elthanan], 1791-1792 (Volume 2, Page 93-94)
      - Beech, [Elnathan], 1795-1798 (Volume 2, Page 98-99)
      - Beldon, John, undated (Volume 2, Page 100)
      - Bell, B., 1793 September 14 (Volume 2, Page 103)
      - Bell, Isabella, 1795 July 26-August 3 (Volume 2, Page 101-102)
      - Bellette, Dugard, undated (Volume 2, Page 108a-108b)
      - Belleville, N., 1792 January 17, 1804 July 25 (Volume 2, Page 106-107)